Um so uh yeah tonight's uh
tonight's suta is um angutaya 1062
uh titled tanha craving
and um
says um the Buddha talks to the monks
and says because this is said no first
point of craving for being is evident
before which there was no craving for
being batana and then that afterwards
then came to be. Still um it is evident
that craving for being depends on this.
In other words um there is no first
point of craving but that doesn't mean
that it doesn't depend on anything that
it's not sustained by anything.
And then the says uh he says I say that
the craving for being has its nutrient.
It's not without nutrient and the
nutrient for craving for being is
ignorance or ravija.
I say that ignorance has its nutrient
and it's not without a nutrient. The
ignor the nutrient for ignorance is the
five hindrances.
I say that the five hindrances have the
nutrient. They're not without the
nutrintment. The nutrient for five
hindrances are three kinds of
misconduct. I say that the three kinds of misconduct
I say that the three kinds of misconduct
have the nutrient. They're not without a
nutrient. And the nutrient for the three kinds of
And the nutrient for the three kinds of
misconduct is the lack of sense
restraint. I say that the lack of sensor straint
I say that the lack of sensor straint
has it nutrient. It's not without a
nutrient. And the nutrient for the lack
of sense restraint is the lack of
recollection and awareness.
I say that the lack of recollection and
the awareness has its nutrient and it's
not without the nutrient and that
nutrient is attention not in the light
of its source. How we translate the yono
manikara the the womb attention or the
attention with the origin or wise
attention doesn't matter how you
translate it basically needs to be
understood. Uh I say that the attention not in the
Uh I say that the attention not in the
light of its source has its nutrient.
It's not without a nutrient. Uh what is
the nutrient for yonicara? And it's the
lack of faith.
I say that the lack of faith has it
nutrient. It's not without the nutrient.
What's the neutrintment for the lack of
faith? It's not listening to the true
teaching. I say that not listening to the true
I say that not listening to the true
teaching has its neutr
for that is not associating with true
persons.
So then the Buddha sums it up. It says
in this way when the factor of not
associating with true persons is
fulfilled it fulfills the factor of not
listening to the true teaching not
hearing it. When the factor of not
listening to the true teaching is
fulfilled it fulfills the factor of the
lack of faith. Uh lack of faith factor
fulfills the factor of uh uh ionara.
Ionisara factor fulfills the factor of
uh lack of sati sanujana
which then fulfills the factor of
lacking the sense restraint lacking the
three kinds of um sorry that results
then in behaving in three kinds of
misconduct that then obviously fulfills
the factor of the five hindrances and
when the five hindrances are fulfilled
they fulfill ignorance. When ignorance
fulfilled, craving for being is there.
It's fulfilled.
So it's like when it rains heavily on a
mountain top and the water flows
downhill to fill the hollows, crevices,
and creeks. And as they become full,
they fill up the pools. The pools fill
up the lakes. The lakes fill up the
streams and the streams fill up the
rivers. The rivers become full, they
fill up the ocean. And that's how the
ocean is nourished and that's how it's
filled up. So then the rest of sages
just goes in the reverse.
So
knowledge and liberation has its
nutrient and it's not without the
nutrient. What's the nutrient for
knowledge and liberation? It's the seven
awakening factors.
Seven awakening factors have has have
the nutrient. The nutrient is the four
foundations of recollection.
The four foundations of recollection
have the nutrient. The nutrient for that
is the three kinds of good conduct.
The three kinds of good conduct have
their nutrient and uh the nutrient for
the three kinds of good conduct is sense
restraint. Sense restraint has its nutrient. It's
Sense restraint has its nutrient. It's
not without the nutrient and the
nutrient for sense restraint is satiampa
recollection awareness have have the
nutrient and it's not without nutrient
and the nutrient for that is attention
in the light of its source or yonara
yonisara has its nutrient and that
nutrientment is faith faith has its
nutrientment that nutrientment is
listening to the true correct teachings
um listening to the uh true teachings
has its instrument and that is
associating with true persons.
So then the Buddha sums it up and again
same it's like um when it rains heavily
on a mountaintop when the water flows
downhill to the hollow crevices creeks
become full fill up the pools fill up
the lakes lakes fill up the streams
streams fill up the rivers and then the
rivers become full and they fill up the
ocean. Um so let's go back to the beginning and
Um so let's go back to the beginning and
start this uh one by one
and um so
so
tanha start with tanha basically so
there is no first point that the craving
that you have in your experience
uh before which it was not to put it
that way before which it didn't exist
and then it just came to being just just
appeared out of nowhere and now it's
there. So in other words, it's the it's
it's the it's the infinite history of um
of relationship of you and and your
tanha. He has no discernable beginning.
So that already indicates that this
dependence that the Buddha then goes
these nutrientments that he goes to
explain are not um sequential things are
not things that are set up in a linear
way whereby the first thing comes to be
that then results in the second thing
that then results in the third thing. So
the relationship of its dependence is
not linear because if it were then the
first point of craving would be
manifested. So that's already something that people
So that's already something that people
would just um uh probably quickly kind
of glance over says the no first point
of craving is evident and there are
other sutas that talk refer to the same
say the same thing about Avija there's
no first point of Avija that's being
manifested yet a vija is not without its
cause. So that's the whole obviously as
we spoke in other talks the whole
principle of the the idea of causality
people need to wrap their head around
and and and understand that it's not um
cause and effect in terms of linear
action reaction but it's that
simultaneous dependence.
So it's like the
the heat of the flame is dependent on
the actual wick burning.
So those are two separate phenomena that
you can discern.
Um but they are not inseparable. You
cannot have the heat without flame or
have a flame that doesn't have a heat,
fire that doesn't burn. So this is this
is this is kind of mirrors the same
relationship. So if you were to look for
the origin before which there was no
craving to see how craving came to be,
you're never going to find it because
that's not how things work in terms of
the the the the phenomena of craving and
so you need to look for the nutrient
that is currently responsible for
maintenance of that infinite of that
craving with its infinite history
to put it that way. And that currently
maintained nutrient that currently
maintains the infinite history of
craving is ignorance. It's a vija.
So you might recognize craving in your
experience in regard to this feeling or in regard
in regard to this feeling or in regard
to that feeling. Obviously you won't be
fully understanding it, but you might be
able to kind of um
uh wrap your head around, let's say,
like let's put it that way. And um so
the whole point then is if your um if if
your vague understanding of u of the
phenomenon of craving
you need to look for what does that
depend on so not in a psychological
manner not in like hm what was before
this thing that I'm aware of now there
is no before
it's more like what is with this thing
that I'm aware of now this craving this
ambiguous sense of craving and pressure
whatever I define it what is with it
what is its nutrient what is its
necessary basis what is its cause
like simultaneously enduring present
cause obviously the Buddha gives you the
obviously the Buddha gives you the
answer it's a vija but now if you
question it rightly
you at least get some idea as to where
to look for that ava so it's not a vija
from the past.
It's not the Avija from the um you know
six years ago or something or or or some
hidden lack of knowledge that you
haven't learned yet. No, it's currently
enduring phenomena that that that
maintains that it's responsible for the
maintenance of another currently
presently enduring phenomena of craving.
So then that Avija
what is it then? So if it is there, if
it has to be there simultaneously
present with the craving because no
first point of craving is evident yet it
depends on something.
So if it depends on something that thing
also has no first point of its origin um
evident either and as I said others
would actually say that directly about
avijia. So what is that avida then when
you have a the phenomenon of craving in
your experience resisting
um craving for more pleasure uh
resisting the discomfort um leaning
towards indolence when the feeling is
neutral what is the common theme of those three
what is the common theme of those three
attitudes?
What is the common thread to all those
three attitudes?
It's ignorance. But what is that
ignorance as a as a like practically
speaking? How does that manifest in your
experience?
So that's that's already a line for
reflection. ignorance ava non-n knowledge of what
ignorance ava non-n knowledge of what
ignoring what how um it's not really
like the the the lack of information as
I said because then if you were to get
the information if ignorance maturity it
would be information
lack of information if you once you
learned information that moment from
then onwards craving would disappear
because you would have removed its
necessary uh uh presently simultaneously
enduring
So it's not that. So what is it then?
Well, I explained that in other talks.
It's the attitude of ignoring, turning a
blind eye, covering up exemplified
through the behaviors of uh avoiding
responsibility for your actions, for
your choices. uh um placing the the the
origin of the pressure of lust or ill
will or or or or other pressures on the
world on the things on the objects of
your attention and so on. So all of
those attitudes maintain ignorance and
that's pretty much exactly what the next
line says. See you start looking for
ignorance. You see it's a certain
attitude of being unable to help
yourself but ignore but actively turn a
blind eye.
And then it's a it's it's a it's a valid
line of reasoning to then ask a further
question. Why is it so? Why is it that I
can't help myself
ignore or or not want to deal with this
or just turn away or not see through
things? Well, it's because of the five
hindrances. So, it's because of those five pressures
So, it's because of those five pressures
of sensuality,
ill will, um laziness, indolence, um
restlessness, and then doubt.
and then doubt.
But now you got to ask yourself okay so
when I have a pressure of doubt or a
pressure of ill will what is my
responsibility there
I mean those things have arisen on their
own sure but what is do I do I have some
input do I have some say in it what do I
do
and again we address that in other talks
but that's basically when you realize oh
you are responsible you're not
responsible for five hindrances coming
pressuring you, but you're responsible
for for for taking them up, for not
seeing through that pressure and taking
it at face value. So when pressure of
sensuality, a hindrance of sensuality
arises, do you see through it as a bait
that you are not picking up or do you
just find yourself already, you know,
full on choking on the bait, already
eating it and taking more? Same with a
will. Same with any other. Are you
already acting out?
That is your input. Are you acting out
of those pressures or you or you remain
there not acting out and not losing
perspective of them?
And that's exactly what the next
paragraph says. The nutrintment for the
five hindrances is acting out. The three
kinds of misconduct. It's basically
acting out on account of these five
pressures by body, speech, and mind.
So the fact that it's rooted in those
five hindrances in those five pressures
that's what makes it a misconduct
doesn't matter if even if the whole
world approves of what you did of what
your conduct was on account of this
pressure or that pressure the fact that
it was rooted in the five hingences and
you took them up at a face value and you
acted out of them it constitutes a
misconduct already. That's the reference
point. not the world, not the tradition,
not the uh the peer pressure, not the
culture, it's whether it's rooted in the
five hindrances.
So if it is, it's a misconduct.
So see how you would have started from
oh craving you know phenomena that I am
sort of I can be aware of but it's
somewhat abstract and it's certainly not
something I can just just uh voluntarily
uh uh put a stop to. just just just
switch it off or something like a like a
like a switch or unplug it. But then as
you start reflecting through you see
that it depends on a certain attitude of
ignoring, turning a blind eye, avoiding
um avoiding transparency basically just
kind of feeling uncomfortable with it,
looking past it, distracting yourself
from it through actions that are
pressuring you towards distraction,
towards lust, towards aversion, towards
these things. But now from that kind of
semi-abstract ambiguous you came down to
three kinds of misconduct.
In other words, choices that you choose
to act out of.
So there is now no more abstraction
there. I mean you can theorize all you
want but the bottom line is whenever you
make a choice to act you choose to do so
and you know it. You can justify it
obviously retroactively and say, "Oh, it
was because of this or because of that."
But when you were making it, you knew
it's because you were making it and
because you were pressured to do it and
you wanted to act out of pressure and
you want to get rid of this comfort and
you acted out. Everything else then any
psychologization that comes afterwards,
it's second to it. So the five
hindrances directly depend on uh acting
out of those five pressures that try to
hinder you through acting by body,
speech and mind.
So those are the actual nutrients for
the five hindrances
and then it goes to say so the next line
of reflection again I mean we follow the
sutas but obviously you can just ask
yourself these things and and look for
these phenomena in your experience. So
three kinds of bodily misconduct. So
whenever you act out of um greed,
aversion, distraction by body, by
speech, by mind, and you don't even have
to go into like two subtle layers of you
know, was this where was this rooted?
What was my intention behind this? Take
the obvious stuff. Sensuality, ill will,
doubt. Just take the obvious stuff and
see ask yourself
acting out of the obvious stuff.
What is the necessary basis for that?
What is the currently simultaneously
simultaneously
enduring present uh uh cause for me to
keep acting out of these things?
Why do I why do I keep like going
towards sensuality or going towards ill
will and so on? Well, because the
pressure got too much.
So you obviously need to train in regard
to the pressure
but you don't start from the from the
from the side of u already being able to
kind of contain and not act out of
pressure. You start from the side of
being completely overwhelmed by the
pressure. That's why virtue has to come
first that creates some sort of
container for you to at least have a
certain line that you will not cross. No
amount of it doesn't matter what what
kind of pressure is put on you to act
and do this.
So
you act out of body speech and mind when
basically you cannot contain you cannot
endure rightly on the right level that
pressure of the hindrances. So then why
can you not endure rightly?
Why do you act out? Well because you
lack sense restraint. You were lacking
foresight in regard to your own capacity
in regard to your own capacity
to withstand and contain and endure the
pressure of hindrances without acting
out. So you went into the unsuitable
sight, sounds, smell, taste, touches.
That's the purpose of sense restraint.
It's not saying no to everything blindly
because it's bad in and of itself. No,
purpose of sense restraint is basically
to enable you in the beginning to be
able to to have some distance between
you and the pressure that's trying to
overwhelm you and push you towards
acting out of body, speech and mind.
So it's like a it's like a it's like an
like an an indirect effect. So you you
foresee like oh if I go in such and such
environment it will be very likely
highly likely that I will that the
pressure towards sensuality or ill will
increase to the point of I don't know if
I will be able to restrain myself.
So then you prevent those scenarios from
arising in the first place. That's the
whole point of restraining eye, ear nose
and so on. So whenever you practice
restraint, you need to practice it with
this context, with this
type of um informed attitude
because that's what gives it its
purpose. I'm not just saying no to
sights and sounds and everything. No,
I'm doing it because I keep an eye on
the mind that's going to be overwhelmed
with the pressure. And if I'm not sure
to what extent, well, to that extent, I
need to be careful how much I expose it.
So that's why the lack of the sense
restraint. So you you're basically
having an active attitude of nonsense
restraint is the simultaneously present nutrient
is the simultaneously present nutrient
for the three kinds of misconduct. When
that attitude builds up, you will act
out because because that's where you're
because because that's where you're
heading basically.
So
what is then the cause for the lack of
sense restraint? What is its nutrient
simultaneously present nutrient? It's
the lack of sati san. So it's the lack
of um nonforgetfulness and awareness. So
it's it's it's a basically it's lacking
uh the recognition of here and now of
the importance of preventing certain
circumstances that would then result in
pressures building up and overwhelming
your mind and not forgetting that. Like
you might feel I feel pretty good today.
my mind feels stable. I I can probably
handle it and so on. But that's not the
point. You remember then that such
environment or a certain environments are always
or a certain environments are always
unbeneficial are always to be avoided
and then you don't compromise that and
then great. If you can handle it,
perfect. But it's even better if there
is nothing to handle to begin with.
And uh on top of it all sooner or later
things will come your way that no amount
of sense restraint will be able to uh
prevent the pressure from coming up. So
that's why you you you practice before
those sickness, aging uh or greater
misfortunes that come and overwhelm your
mind through exactly through sense
restraint. So to be able to contain the
pressure and then learning how to not
act out of your own pressure of your own
chitta. So that's why lacking the
attitude of that right memory like
literally like remembering the right
things the the things that are important
to you forgeth you know stop you stop
thinking about it. Sure if somebody were
to ask you you would remember but you
you're not actively having it there as a
as a as a kind of framework of your
actions and choices throughout the day.
What you're going to look at see taste
smell and so on. Where you going to go
who you going to talk to who you going
to meet and so on. But if you do not
forget what's important,
what's important,
then those choices when they present
themselves will be put in the right
light. Oh,
I could go over there and see such and
such person, but last time I was there,
I got really wound up and um and my mind
overwhelmed and I said stuff I shouldn't
and so on. So, it's like, oh, I better
restrain myself. Same. or or go to like
a like I don't know parties with alcohol
and stuff where priestesses will be
compromised which will then result in
compromising everything else. That all
comes out of basically lacking
recollection and awareness correctly uh
lacking the the the remembering of
what's important to you.
Um and then says so what is the reason
for lacking that? What what is the
reason for you forgetting stuff?
And the reason is
so attention not in the light of its
source. So in other words, the reason
for that is that when you do because
your attention always has to rest on
things on stuff sides, sounds melt
touches thoughts.
But that doesn't mean that you need to
ignore the background of it, the
context. So whenever your attention is resting on
So whenever your attention is resting on
something at the back of your mind it's
going to be already a form of subtle
implicit reason for resting on those
things. That reason can be neutral but it can be
That reason can be neutral but it can be
uh unh wholesome.
It can be wholesome, unh wholesome and
neutral in a sense that you could have a
good reason to be attending to this. You
could have a bad reason to be attending
this. I agree aversion delusion non-grid
non aversion don't non delusion or you
could have a neutral reason for
attending to this but the point is
either of those reasons if you are not
discerning the reason for your attention
resting on that simultaneous to your
attention resting on those things you
are in the state of
and that's the point here
so it's not just I need to have a good
reason you need to know the reason So
So
whenever you find your mind in a certain
state or find your thoughts occupied
with certain things instead of trying to
uh uh resolve and manage the feeling
that came with it whether it's pleasant,
unpleasant or neutral, you want to see
the backdrop of it. In other words,
what is the reason for my attention
revolving around this or resting on
these things? Not change it. Not get
focused on something else. Either way,
the reason of your focusing will be
unknown. It will be ioniso.
So
if you find yourself basically
not wanting to think about it or not
wanting to drill these things like h why
am I doing this? Why am I think this?
Why is my attention resting on this?
Because it's kind of bothersome for
sure, cumbersome,
unpleasant. like
it's it's just not something that you
would naturally want to do. Um and
that's why you're kind of avoiding doing
it. And if you ask yourself well okay
now say you learn that no you need to do
this whenever you find your attention
resting or something or planning
something you need to know on the basis
of what is this happening
and you're always going to boil down to
basically as I said before it's going to
be either um on the basis of pleasant
feeling you're leaning towards wanting
it more the basis of unpleasant feeling
you're kind of resisting it or the basis
of like a neutral feeling that's already
causing a certain certain kind of unease
and you want to be oblivious to it. It
doesn't it doesn't go into some as I
said great ancient history that you need
to discern where it all came to be. It's
right there. All of these things are
simultaneously there just layers of the
same principle.
So
why are you then not
always aware of the background
in that indirect sense like you know I
can I can be attending to this or to
that but I can at the same time know why
am I doing that I can see where it's
rooted I can see whether it's kind of uh
wholesome whether it's unh wholesome
whether it's neutral and that's the
important part to see it so why are you
not seeing it is because you haven't
drilled it deep enough. You haven't
practiced it. You haven't made the
effort to actually look that way
sufficiently enough.
There is not there's like you you
haven't trained yourself basically.
So why haven't you done that? Well, it's
because you lacked faith.
And lacking faith doesn't mean you
lacked some, you know, inspiration on
the level of of poetry or uplifted
spirit of the Buddhist words or
something. No, it means you lacked
faith. Means basically uh
it didn't really you refused to um to
believe how important that is to practice this
how important that is to practice this
yoniso
like you lacked faith basically means
you lacked the belief in in importance
of application of it. That's what it
means. You dismissed it. You heard it, but you
You dismissed it. You heard it, but you
thought, well, yeah, sure, there could
be one aspect of it, but I prefer this
as and then you kind of concocted your
own thing and you haven't done the
drilling. So
So
why wouldn't a person lack faith? Why
wouldn't a person not drill in the
importance of this principle? Why would
it kind of brush it off or dismiss it or
or change it into something else?
Well, because they haven't learned how
important it is. In other words, they
haven't listened to the actual dharma.
They might have been hearing things
about a dharma, but that's not
necessarily the true teaching. So, not
everybody who speaks the dharma, even if
they just parrot the Buddha's words, is
speaking the tr the true teaching. The
the true teaching is the teaching that
emphasizes things that should be
emphasized, not just parrots what somebody else says
not just parrots what somebody else says
and then leaves you to figure it out or
make your own way whatever feels right
to you.
So if a person lacks faith to to to uh
sustain the application of constant
questioning of
why is my attention resting on this?
What's the back backdrop? What's the
back state of of of my mind? Where is my
mind leaning? Um
it's because they haven't as I said uh
uh accepted the fact that it's really
important. They don't believe it's
important to do it. and they don't
believe it's important to do it because
they haven't really uh heard or listened
or or understood enough of why it is
important to do it. So they haven't or
they never heard somebody emphasizes
that as really important thing and
that's why they never really paid much
attention to it or they might have heard
it and then they dismissed it.
So why would they then not have listened
to the true teaching
and the nutrient is because they were
not associating with true persons other
words with right people with people that
can actually teach them this and being
associating with them doesn't mean
socializing and just sitting in their
company and and soaking up their
spiritual energy. No means hearing this
from somebody who understood it.
So you want to learn a craft, you need
to go to somebody who knows the craft,
who actually can teach you and can
explain in their own words the
principles behind it, not just sort of
uh recite the government curriculum or
something. Um so that's what it means
not associating with true persons. Now
you can ask yourself, well why have I
not been associating with true people,
with people that know the dhamma? And
that's where things get obviously like
you start questioning yourself and they
can be well maybe because you never met
one maybe maybe you might have met them
and dismissed them. Maybe you didn't
like their energy or something and you
didn't want to listen what they had to
say. Uh maybe you liked everything but
you haven't actually paid attention to
what's being said. Like so even people
that you associated yourself with in
terms of learning the dharma
it's like have I really
unequivocally understood for myself what
they emphasize
and seen that as as beneficial or or not
as beneficial. So in other words you
can't just sit and listen to the dhamma
even if it's the Buddha himself talking.
You need to make the effort to
understand it. And that's that other
suta that says the the the factor for
the rising of the right view is
utterance of another of somebody who
understood it who knows how to teach
you. Uh which would be the equivalent of
associating with the true person. But
then the other factor is that
so it's already being able
to have the context on your reactions to
what you hear and not just take them at
face value. I like this. I don't like
this. One of the reasons uh that the Buddha
One of the reasons uh that the Buddha
said a person wouldn't get the right
view uh even if they are being taught by
the Buddha himself is they have the
attitude of finding faults. So they're
looking for faults. That's already
coming out of the preference that's not
being addressed through yonisara. See, I
have a preference. I like things. I
dislike things. I hear this person
speak, I don't like it.
But if I'm myself interested in my own
welfare, in my own benefit, I can't take
that at face value and just dismiss them
because I don't like it. Equally, I
can't at the face value accept them
because I like how they speak.
We're back on to Yoniso. Either way, I
need to know
where is this leaning, this preference,
where is it rooted? What is my
motivation? What is my intention? What
is the reason like simultaneously
enduring reason for my dislike or like
and then put it in that context.
So, I really dislike what this person's
saying, but I see that as a mere
emotional preference that I cannot
rationally justify if I'm honest and
transparent. So then, if you are
actually clear, even with all the
dislike you have, you're still going to
be hearing what they say and you'll be
able to actually think about it and take
it on and really investigate for
yourself. Oh, so he emphasizes this and
I really dislike him. I can't stand him.
But what he's saying
reminds me of this suta or reminds me of
that suta. So maybe there is something
more to it. So let me try and apply it.
I still hate him, but let me try and
apply it. Basically, that's how you
progress. Doesn't matter. You put your
preference aside. Same. I'm just so
inspired by this person. He's just when
he speaks like for days, I'm just just
sort of floating. Just nothing can touch
me because my mind is so uplifted. It's
like, yeah, but have you understood what
are they saying?
Are they reciting poetic verses to you
or or are they actually telling you what
the Buddha was saying?
So you might be inspired all you want,
but if you start thinking about what's
being emphasized and what the practice
is for me to do, you wouldn't see it if
it's adding up or not adding up. And if
you're inspired by somebody, but things
are not adding up, you'll know which one
to emphasize yourself. You need to
emphasize adding up of practice.
Inspiration or non is secondary. Same if
you're really annoyed by somebody but
what they're saying is really adding up
again you will be able to not act out of
that preference. But for that a person
every individual person needs to make
that effort to to like uncover that
those preferences uncover the roots of
those preferences. That's why that's
already the beginning of yoniso. That's
that's that transparency that we often
talk about. So neither of these things
are just kind of circumstantial factors.
They're just one slots into the other
into the other. All of these things are
basically results of the layers upon
layers upon layers of your own attitude,
of your own overlooking, of your own
lack of transparency, of your own acting
out.
So then um
so then in in reverse basically
he goes to say that knowledge and
liberation is pretty much the result of
the opposite. So full enlightenment is
the result of the opposite nothing else.
And I think there was a talk I did a
long time ago it's like self honesty can
make you hunt or something like that
which basically talks exactly about
this. If you start with a transparency
which is already the beginning of the
yoniso and obviously yes if you hear somebody
and obviously yes if you hear somebody
emphasizing things that need to be
emphasized uh you won't fall into a trap dismissing
uh you won't fall into a trap dismissing
it on a kind of preference or glorifying
it on a kind of preference either way
not doing it. You'll actually be doing
it and trying to see it for yourself.
That trans transparency
would then lead to basically you
associating with with with true persons.
In other words, listening to them,
learning from them more and more and
more, which increases transparency and
obviously increases the field of
knowledge that can then help you discern
things. Um that would then lead to the
um listening to the actual true teaching
obviously like um being able to
recognize the true teaching as well for
yourself. Then you wouldn't have a problem to
Then you wouldn't have a problem to
believe that doing these
drills and trainings of constantly
unraveling and uncovering where your
intention uh and motivation is rooted in
regard to everything that you do or
choose to attend. You would have faith
in that like you wouldn't need to
convince yourself that I need to keep
training this because you already on
account of associating learning about
the right emphasis you already have a
good grasp that that's what need to be
emphasized you might be careless and not
do it but you certainly would have
enough faith and belief in actually
applying it
if you do that long enough you would
have sufficiently developed the yonika
so you would have learned as a mode of
being to whenever you attend to things,
you're attending them with a corner of
your eye being aware of its source,
knowing its basis, knowing the
motivation behind your actions in regard
to anything. Doesn't matter how subtle
or big or small, fast or slow.
But that can only come with constantly
uncovering that, learning to question
yourself. So transparency
So transparency
listening to that teaching you would
obviously believe then in the
application of it and then you would be
through doing it you would be developing
that very yonisara which then means you
would be recollected and aware. You
would not be forgetful of things that
are important to you because even in if
the things are way too pre way too busy,
too many moving parts, you can't follow
every single instance of it because it's
just too many things happening. The
broad picture remains visible like you
know things that you wouldn't do. You
know things that should be deemphasized
and not engaged with and you don't
forget that. Simply through not
forgetting that the mind cannot
overwhelm you or make you uh make
choices that would then take you in the
unsuitable environments that would then
result in increase of the pressure that
you cannot possibly control and then you
would act out.
So transparency the same thread would
then uh result in fulfillment of the
sense restraint. So the same thread that
then maintains
knowing what's important is then the
thread that makes you actually exercise
that. Oh, because uh this passion is
important to me, I won't go to a crazy
music festival with alcohol and drugs
and everything else.
Obviously, I'm giving the course
examples, but the same principle can
then be applied to lots of other things
where you see a direct correlation. If I
go there, this is what's going to
result. Like even if somehow magically I
managed to restrain myself in terms of
not act out I already lost the restraint
by choosing to go in that environment in
the first place because it's completely
unnecessary. So then if you are fulfilling sense
So then if you are fulfilling sense
restraint if you never compromise on the
level of your choice like sure if you
end up in this environment completely
out of your hand that's a different
story but the the the the the factor there is
but the the the the the factor there is
whether you chose it whether you chose
to give into those things on that level.
If you did well that's what we just
discussed that's why you would not be
able to sustain uh mindfulness and not
acting out of pressure.
But here in reverse through that
transparency if you are now sustaining
the three kinds of good conduct in other
words you don't act out of pressure
because you are uh not willingly
choosing to compromise sense restraint
because you're not willingly choosing to
stop questioning yourself.
Then those three kinds of conduct would
have created a container whereby
basically you cannot possibly even if
you want to lose the sight of the the
peripheral of the motivation of the
intention behind your actions of your
situation as a whole without needing to
police it, without needing to chase it,
without needing to dissect it. The
framework becomes pretty quite
unshakable or certainly more unshakable
than it was before. And that results in
uh in basically the four foundations of
recollection which then obviously means if you are
which then obviously means if you are
whether sitting, walking, standing,
laying down in regard to body feeling in
regard to these cornerstones so to speak
of where where people would cover up
would make choices uh uh that are
infected with greed, aversion, delusion.
If you basically uh now through what we
described cannot lose the sight of that
you are fulfilling the seven awakening
factors. So through through the three
kinds of good conduct you are fulfilling
seven awakening factors. Basically uh uh
uh fulfillment of satipatana is the
result of the three kinds of good
conduct as we did as we discussed in
just previous sutas
ago. So the seven awakening factors lead to
So the seven awakening factors lead to
knowledge and liberation.
Again that's the result of fulfilling
them. And this is again just goes back
to what we speak so so often so many
times. It's like there's no special
practice. There's no luck involved either. There
There's no luck involved either. There
is certainly no mystical experience that
just doing random stuff would come up
and then make everything fall into
place. is just training of a layer upon
layer upon layer upon layer. And this
suta so so quite quite well it describes
what those layers are and it describes
pretty much why you wouldn't be
developing them
as we just addressed it. Um, so it's
like the most direct and comprehensive
way to enlightenment. And it's like
there's really nothing else needed need
that you need to do on top of on top of
what we just described. And there's
nothing that you need to wait for in a
sense because all these things are
always with you
in any at any given time in any
experience or reason for whatever it
was. whatever it is. So,
So,
let's see. We got a few more questions.
Right. So yeah, I think I kind of
already answered it, but yeah, there's a
question like, so how do you practice
yonisara? How do you attend in light of
its attention source?
Um the practical example, what what do
you do? So do you do you learn how to
shift your attention, how to look? It's
like all of those things, you know, can
maybe help you
um become more informed about it, but
fundamentally you do it by uncovering
the intentions behind your actions and
be behind your your attention. Whatever
you're choosing to attend, you always
need to have a degree of self-awareness
revealed through self-questing as to why
am I attending to this?
Why am I preferring this? Again, not in
order to find some psychological linear
first point where these things came up.
No, it's right there and then. Why? Oh,
it's because it's pleasant.
Oh, it's because it bothers me. Oh, it's
because of this, because of that.
Knowing that, no, you don't need to
resolve it. That's the point. There is
no resolution. It's just that's the
reason and that's what you're doing. But
it's the non it's the ignoring of that
relationship. That's this whole thing we've been
That's this whole thing we've been
describing and the yonisar is the
beginning of non- ignoring of that
relationship. So that's why although um people might
So that's why although um people might
be asking oh why am I doing this why am
I doing that they still doing it with
another intention behind that action
which is to resolve it
to figure it out. It's like no you're
doing it only to the extent to reveal it
then of course you don't act out you
don't break the precepts but you don't
try to get rid of it because if you try
to get rid of it through this denial you
are getting rid of the relationship of
yon so which means something else is now
yoniso and you're not seeing it
so
questioning self questioning that points
back to the direction of the source of
your current situation which is going to
be as I said you'll be doing something
thinking something attending to
something sight sounds smell taste
touches or thoughts has to be something
and you always want to have that
knowledge as to why
oh because I prefer it or don't prefer I
must change it no you don't need to
change it you contain it through not
acting out and then you reveal it that's
the practice of yonisu
and that obviously that practice if you
the more you question yourself the
easier it would become like you wouldn't
even need to go through the like
formally uttering questions and so on.
It just already become your attitude of
just seeing what's behind this because
you already know where to look. But
that's not going to just magically
manifest itself come like fall from the
sky. That's the attitude that you will
have if you if you develop it and if you
don't use it you will lose it basically
and that's u yeah. So then the second
question is look why does the practice
of sati then why is recollectness why is
the non-forgetfulness dependent on this
dependent on this attitude of discerning
the intention behind your actions
seeing the currently enduring motivation
for the for your attention resting on
this or that choosing to attend this as
opposed to that.
Well, we we addressed it. We did, didn't
we? We basically the the reason why it's
because that already gives you the the
the the broadest framework of what's
important and what should be emphasized.
And if you're if you lose the sight of
that, then you forget.
So, think of it like basically say you
are at a crossroads
and you're not committing to any
direction. You stay there on the
crossroads
and then doesn't matter what comes from
what side you will see there. You will
recognize it. You won't forget about it.
But if you forget about the importance
of staying at the crossroads, staying at
the origin of this of this traffic and
you choose one of the lanes, one of the
directions, well, you it will be
impossible for you to remember about the
other three and what's on them because
you're not there now seeing it.
and what would have passed and taken
those directions you wouldn't see either
because you already narrowed down you
already went down one direction and lost
the sight of the other three. So that's
why sati depends on it.
So through selfquesting
you develop recollectiveness
you develop the non- losing of the right
context. Um
Um
so yeah um also like somebody pointed
out that um the simile that the Buddha
gives it sort of shows that it's not
like um
um the things are not sequential in a
sense that uh you know like uh the
origin of the mountain then fills up the
pool and then that pool goes into the
stream and that stream goes into the
river. No, the origin from the mountain
continues filling up. So the pool is
filled up and the water's still coming.
So the streams are filled up and the
water's still coming. And that's that
common thread that I've been saying. The
common thread that starts with your
transparency and all the way to
knowledge and liberation. That's the
water still coming.
The effort to uncover the principle, not
ignore it is what will fuel this whole
thing. What will fill it up? So it's not
just like one, two, three, four, five.
It's just one thread intensifying and
filling up everything in its way. Um so so
[Music]
right so then there's another question
um slightly more um well it's it's still
kind of related but so yeah the suta
describes the connection between the
five hindrances and the three ways of
misconduct. So the hindrances are fed
So the hindrances are fed
by the way you act.
Um but hindrance of themselves are not
actions. Yeah, that's correct. We
already said that. Like they are
basically baits traps as the Buddha said
in that suta. Um the things that arise
that like if you don't attend
with the knowledge of the source of your
attention while you're attending it,
that's how you get hooked so to speak.
So when he was talking about sensuality,
he didn't say that the the I don't know
the say beautiful sights, beautiful
sights are not sensuality. It's not a
hindrance. People think like oh seeing
this, smelling this, hearing this,
thinking this, that's a hindrance. It's
not. That's what comes up that you don't
see through which is what hinders you.
So technically it's your lack of yoniso
that hinders you in these specific
situations. Um so when the Buddha said um if the one
Um so when the Buddha said um if the one
does not attend rightly I attend with
its source to the sight of the beauty
that's when sensuality hindrance of
sensuality is there. If he attends to it
rightly then basically that thing
remains that the the the the phenomenon
of beauty the sight of beauty remains
there. So the thing has arisen the bait
is still there but it doesn't hinder
you. So hindrances in themselves are not
So hindrances in themselves are not
actions but it's if you if you don't see
through them so to speak if you attend
to them without the knowledge of the
source while you're attending it the
source of your very attention as to why
you're doing it uh that's what hinders
you. So, so that's why like um that whole
So, so that's why like um that whole
kind of um the relationship is not
something you can just stop as I said
well none of this you could just stop
craving you can't stop hindrances you
can't just stop but as we just uncovered
through the suta
where the line where the threshold of
your input is begins and ends and that
is what you're responsible for and if
you stick to that if you practice that
sufficient ma then it will drain away so
then the sight of the beauty doesn't
matter how many times it will come up
for an arunter and anagami
he's incapable of attending to it
without the light of its origin. In
other words, he cannot possibly engage
in a soul in regard to things that
remain standing in the world.
So that's another reason why it's
important to not just blindly try to get
rid of the hindrance and do the opposite
and manage it and remove because you're
trying to remove the whole thing. You're
picking up the bait because you say the
bait is the problem and I get hooked
because this thing is in front of my
eyes. No, you get hooked because you
grabbed it. Can remain standing in front
of your eyes all you want. If you don't
reach for it, it can't hook you. As
simple as that.